ILGWU Union Health Center Records 5780/060
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Union Health Center Records
1910-1984
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Union Health Center
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU)
5780/060
7 cubic feet
7 linear ft.
Administrative records, annual reports, articles, correspondence, financial records.
Correspondence, annual reports, articles, financial statements, and other materials documenting the evolving role of the ILGWU Union Health Center.
3676406
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, October 14, 2008
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 10, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
In 1913, the New York City locals of the ILGWU established the Union Health Center (UHC), under the direction of Dr. George Price of the Joint Board of Sanitary Control. Initially, the UHC offered physical exams, medical treatments, access to a dental clinic, and information about health and hygiene. For a period, the center operated through a cooperative plan, with patients paying a fee and the union subsidizing the rest of the cost of the visit. During the Depression, the cost of running the center was met by other means. This included getting other local unions in New York City, such as the electrical workers, metal workers, letter carriers, post office clerks, and pocketbook workers, to affiliate with the UHC, as well as winning an official endorsement from the Central Labor Union of New York. Beginning in the 1940s, New York City manufacturers agreed to contribute to a fund that would cover the cost of medical services provided to members at the UHC.
By the 1960s, the UHC offered comprehensive care to ILGWU members and their families, and over the years, the center's range of services expanded to include social and psychological services, eye exams, maternity care, and surgical consultation. The Union Health Center continues its work today at 275 Seventh Avenue, in New York City.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Union Health Center document the evolving role of the center. Included are general correspondence, meeting minutes of the UHC's medical board, annual reports on the UHC's activities to the General Executive Board, triennial reports to delegates at the ILGWU's international conventions, and related published materials. Much of this material is routine or administrative in nature.
In both collections that comprise the records of the Union Health Center, there are articles by such figures as George M. Price and Pauline Newman on union health centers in general and the ILGWU Center in particular. The publications of the Union Health Center primarily document the educational efforts of the center, providing information about the center, its services, and its activities. Also included are pamphlets about the ILGWU's health and welfare benefits program and publications from the Joint Board of Sanitary Control.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/171: ILGWU Union Health Center Publications
Clothing workers--Labor unions--New York (State)--New York.; Clothing workers--Health and hygiene--New York (State)--New York.; Clothing trade-- Employees--Medical care--New York (State)--New York.; Health promotion--New York (State)--New York.; Labor union members--Health and hygiene--New York (State)--New York.; Medical centers-- New York (State)--New York.; Medical centers--Administration.; Newman, Pauline.; Price, George M. (George Moses), 1864-1942.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Union Health Center.
3676406
- General Correspondence, 1927-1932 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- General Correspondence, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- General Correspondence, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- General Correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- General Correspondence [folder 1 of 2], 1937 (Box 1, Folder 5a)
- General Correspondence [folder 2 of 2], 1937 (Box 1, Folder 5b)
- General Correspondence, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- General Correspondence, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- General Correspondence, 1943-1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- General Correspondence, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- General Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- General Correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- General Correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- General Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- General Correspondence, 1955-1957 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- General Correspondence, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- General Correspondence, 1961-1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Adopted Children, World War II, 1948-1952 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Articles by Pauline Newman, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Many are undated.
- Broadcasts, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Finances [folder 1 of 3], 1945-1956 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Budgets, fees, salaries for medical staff.
- Finances [folder 2 of 3], 1945-1956 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Finances [folder 3 of 3], 1945-1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Form letters, 1928-1935 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Health Plans of Locals [folder 1 of 2], 1930-1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Health Plans of Locals [folder 2 of 2], 1930-1959 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- History of the Union Health Center. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Minutes of Medical Board meetings, reports and memos, 1931-1936 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Minutes, 1937-1939 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Minutes, 1940-1943 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Minutes, 1944-1946 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Minutes, 1947-1950 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Minutes, 1951-1960 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Minutes, 1961-1977 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Newsletters, 1926-1951 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Notes, personal memos. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Office Employees' International Union, Local 153, 1943-1946 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Office Employees' International Union, Local 153, 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Office Employees' International Union, Local 153, 1949-1951 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Office Employees' International Union, Local 153, 1952-1956 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Price, George, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Programs, 1930-1949 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Starr, Mark, 1936-1951 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- A Study of the Health Protection Afforded Members of the ILGWU, by Francis T. Dover, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  March 1939.
- Newspaper Clippings. [folder 1 of 3] (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Newspaper Clippings. [folder 2 of 3] (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Newspaper Clippings. [folder 3 of 3] (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Annual Report, 1911 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Oct. 1911.
- Annual Report, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Dec. 1912.
- Annual Report, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  December 1913.
- Annual Report, 1914 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  October 1914.
- Annual Report, 1915 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  October 1915.
- Annual Report, 1916 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  October 1916.
- Annual Report, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  Seventh Year Work and Progress, October 1917.
- Annual Report, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Annual Report, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Annual Report, 1922 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Annual Report, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Annual Report, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Report, Fifteenth Anniversary, 1910-1925 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Annual Report, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Annual Report, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  From Medical and Dental Departments.
- Report, 21st Anniversary of the Union Health Center, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Report of the Director, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Report of the Director, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Report of the Director, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Report to the 23rd Convention, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  May 1937.
- Report to the 24th Convention., 1913-1940 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Annual Report, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Annual Report, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Annual Report, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Annual Report, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Triennial Report, 1944-1946 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Triennial Report, 1947-1949 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Report of the UHC Committee of the G.E.B., 1948-1949 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Report of the UHC Committee of the G.E.B., 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Report of the UHC Committee of the G.E.B., 1954 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Report of the UHC Committee of the G.E.B., 1955 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Report of the UHC Committee of the G.E.B., 1956 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Report of the UHC Committee of the G.E.B., 1957 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Report of the UHC Committee of the G.E.B., 1958 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Report of the UHC Committee of the G.E.B., 1959 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Report of the UHC Committee of the G.E.B., 1960 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Report of the UHC Committee of the G.E.B., 1961-1962 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Report of the UHC Committee of the G.E.B., 1963 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Report of the UHC Committee of the G.E.B., 1964 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Report of the UHC Committee of the G.E.B., 1965 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Report of the UHC Committee of the G.E.B., 1966 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Report of the UHC Committee of the G.E.B., 1967 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Report of the UHC Committee of the G.E.B., 1968 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Report of the UHC Committee of the G.E.B., 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Report of the UHC Committee of the G.E.B., 1975 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Report, UHC financial statement, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Report, UHC financial statement, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Report, UHC financial statement, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Report, UHC financial statement, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Report, UHC financial statement, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Report, UHC financial statement, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Report, UHC financial statement, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Report, UHC financial statement, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Report, UHC financial statement, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Report, UHC financial statement, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Report, monthly departmental activities of the UHC, 1951-1960 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Are Labor's Health Centers A Threat to Doctors?, 1954 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  Reprint, Medical Economics, Inc. October 1954.
- Union Benefits, Medical and Other Benefits in Labor Organizations. By George M. Price, 1918 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  Presented to the ILGWU Convention May 1918.
- Bulletins. Joint Board of Sanitary Control in the Cloak, Suit and Skirt Industry, no.1-4, 1911 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Bulletins. Joint Board of Sanitary Control, no.5-6, 1912 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Bulletins. Joint Board of Sanitary Control, no.7-10, 1913 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Bulletin of the Joint Board of Sanitary Control., 1914 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  May 1914.
- Manufacturers' Bulletin of the Joint Board of Sanitary Control., 1914 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  September 1914.
- Workers' Bulletin of the Joint Board of Sanitary Control, 1914 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  vol. 1 no. 3, September 1914.
- Bulletins. Workers' Health Bulletin, 1915 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  English, Yiddish, Italian
- Bulletins. Joint Board of Sanitary Control, 1915 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Bulletins. Joint Board of Sanitary Control, 1919-1920 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  vol. 1, no. 1, August 1919. vol. 1, no. 2, September 1919. vol. 1, no. 3, October 1919. vol. 2, no. 4, January 1920.
- Ceremonies and Inspection of Facilities Marking the Completion of the Expansion Program, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  February 19, 1949.
- Cleveland Health Center., 1951 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  Official opening Nov. 17, 1951.
- The Union Dental Clinic, 1918 (Box 10, Folder 15)
- Dental Department, 10th Anniversary, 1917-1927 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  May 1917-27.
- Dental Department report, 1931 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  Includes pamphlet (n.d.).
- Department for Social Welfare, New York City. Report on Union Health Center, 1935-1940 (Box 10, Folder 18)
- Education and Social Service Department, 1935-1964 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  Reports.
- Fee Schedule, Union Health Center, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 20)
- Fiftieth Anniversary Celebration of the Union Health Center, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  Programs, plans, lists.
- Fire Hazards in Factory Buildings, 1915 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  December 1915.
- Fire Hazards in Factory Buildings, 1923 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Fire Protection. Manufacturers' Bulletin, 1915 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  Issued by the Jt. Board. of Sanitary Control, March 1915.
- Four Hundred Prescriptions per Day Filled by A Labor Union", by Peter Kamitchis., 1949 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  Reprint from American Druggist, November 1949.
- Graphic Report of the Health Programs of ILGWU Locals, 1940 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Health Center News., 1926-1932 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Health News, 1931 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  Published by the New York State Department of Health, July 1931.
- Health Services, dedicated to the delegates, Golden Jubilee Convention, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 9)
- History in the Making, by Max Meyer, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  Address before the Eighth Annual Congress on Industrial Health of the AMA.
- If I am not for Myself, Who will be for Me? By George M. Price, 1914 (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Justice, reprints (re Union Health Center,), 1943-1946 (Box 11, Folder 13)
- Labor laws re women workers, 1920-1939 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  Articles, unpublished, manuscripts.
- Laundry Minimum Wage Board, 1937-1938 (Box 11, Folder 15)
- Local Health Plans, 1951 (Box 11, Folder 16)
- Manual for the Medical Staff, 1960 (Box 11, Folder 17)
- Medal for a Union, Fifty Years of the Union Health Center, 1914-1964 (Box 11, Folder 18)
- Menu Fourth Anniversary of the Foundation of the Jt. Board. of Sanitary Control., 1914 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  Oct. 1914.
- Minutes (reports of), luncheon meetings, 1969-1970 (Box 11, Folder 20)
- Miscellaneous documents. (Box 11, Folder 21)
- Miscellaneous documents. (Box 11, Folder 22)
- Newsletter, Bulletin for the Medical Staff, 1950-1951 (Box 11, Folder 23)
- Price, George M., articles. [folder 1 of 4] (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Price, George M., articles. [folder 2 of 4] (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Price, George M., articles. [folder 3 of 4] (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Price, George M., articles. [folder 4 of 4] (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Price, George M., biographical material. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  Some correspondence. w. Leo Price.
- Price, Leo, articles. (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Questions and Answers, by Pauline Newman., 1940 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  Issued by the Education of the Union Health Center.
- Reports of the Union Health Center, 1944-1945 (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Sanitary Conditions in the Shops of the Dress and Waist Industry., 1913 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  Report by the Joint Board of Sanitary; Control. May 1913.
- Sanitorium Association Report to the 14th Convention, 1918 (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Seating and Posture. An inquiry made by the Jt. Board. of Sanitary Control into the conditions in the women's garment trades., 1923 (Box 12, Folder 11)
- Security on the March. Health and welfare services of the ILGWU., 1954 (Box 12, Folder 12)
- Sick Benefits to Dressmakers' Union Local 22. Report on the medical administration of., 1935 (Box 12, Folder 13)
- Sick Benefits. Recommendations for claimants. (n.d.) (Box 12, Folder 14)
- Survey of the Union Health Center, by Henry B. Makeover, M.D., 1952 (Box 12, Folder 15)
- A Survey of the Union Health Centers., 1958 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  Published by the American Medical Association.
- Union Health Center of the ILGWU., 1953 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  Reprint from Industrial Medicine and Surgery, Oct 1953
- The Union Health Center of the ILGWU. By Pauline Newman. (Box 12, Folder 18)
  6 pp.
- The Union Health Center of the ILGWU., 1954 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  Extract from Public Health Service publication no. 329, Management Health Medical Programs.
- The Union Health Center. Health Department of Organized Labor, report., 1930 (Box 12, Folder 20)
- The Union Health Center. Health Department of Organized Labor, report, 1913-1931 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- The Union Health Center. Health Department of Organized Labor, report, 1913-1934 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- The Union Health Center, Its Growth and Success. By Pauline Newman. Industrial Bulletin, 1952 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  September 1952.
- United Nations Commission on the Status of Women., 1967 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  Attended by Pauline Newman.
- You and the Union Health Center. (n.d.) (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Your Union Health Center. Information Bulletin, 1956 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Nurses Guild. Audits, correspondence., minutes, rules, regulations., 1954-1968 (Box 13, Folder 7)
- 21st Annual Report of the Union Health Center, 1964 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Annual Report of the Union Health Center, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Annual Report of the Union Health Center, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Interim Report of the Union Health Center, 1944-1945 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Report of the Union Health Center Committee of the General Executive Board, 1946 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  June
- Union Health Center Board Meetings, 1949 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  May 4, July 26, November 2
- Union Health Center Committee Reports, 1951-1953 (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Union Health Center Committee Report, 1970 (Box 14, Folder 8)
- Union Health Center Committee Report, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Union Health Center Committee Report, 1972 (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Union Health Center Committee Report, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 11)
- Union Health Center Budget, 1949-1951 (Box 14, Folder 12)
- Union Health Center Formulary, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 13)
- Union Health Center pamphlets (Box 14, Folder 14)
- Los Angeles Union Health Center, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  Report of Organization and Operation